<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Douglas Tarr]]></title>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-14T10:02:01-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://douglastarr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Douglas Tarr]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working on our Scratch game - Week 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/working-on-our-scratch-game-week-7/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-14T09:50:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/working-on-our-scratch-game-week-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The promise of this class is that kids would have their own working game.  So, this week, they just got to work on their game using all that they knew about Scratch.</p>

<p>Everyone worked on their individual games, and I saw some really cool ideas.</p>

<p>Rather than talk to much about the class, I&rsquo;ve started to reflect on what I&rsquo;ve learned about teaching coding.</p>

<p><img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/scratch-code.png" alt="Scratch Code" /></p>

<h2>Learnings</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Laptops are hard for kids to code on.  We hit lots of frustrating bugs related to slow latops, using touchpads, and weird browser interactions.</p></li>
<li><p>The kids love Scratch!   It lets them express their creativity in a new way.</p></li>
<li><p>Most of the problems in class happen when their code &ldquo;doesn&rsquo;t work&rdquo;.  Then, they are completely blocked.  Sometimes, it&rsquo;s not obvious (even to me) what happened and why it doesn&rsquo;t work, and can take me a while to figure it out.    As they try to build more sophisticated programs, the problems get harder to solve.</p></li>
<li><p> Kids enjoy coding together &ndash; they are always looking at what each other is working on and makes it more fun.</p></li>
<li><p>Scheduling is painful.  Every child has so much to do in their schedule, and they want to be in class with a particular set of other kids, and it quickly turns into a very hard math problem.   I&rsquo;ve got a set of other kids who might want to participate, but I am having trouble integrating the schedules effectively.</p></li>
<li><p>Coding is more than just computer science math.  Kids are spending a lot of their time making songs, drawing, creating little &ldquo;theatrical animations&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>There&rsquo;s a lot of math that they haven&rsquo;t yet learned in school.  They have to master Cartesian coordinates, how to manipulate negative numbers, and a lot of other things.  So, I find myself teaching a lot of math so that you can get your game to have a character jump up and down.</p></li>
<li><p>We probably don&rsquo;t need to &ldquo;move on&rdquo; from Scratch for a while.  There is a lot to do there and I think it will take some time to master.</p></li>
<li><p>Different kids like different things.  I&rsquo;ve got a few kids who love performing, music and singing, and they spend a lot of their time making &ldquo;arrangements&rdquo;.  Some others just love hacking on video games.  Some are just naturally curious and enjoy learning technologies.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Next Steps</h2>

<p>Next week is our final week of this 8 week class, and hopefully the kids will feel like it was enjoyable and that they learned some new things about computers and programming.</p>

<p>We are going to start a new session in the new year, and I&rsquo;m pleased to announce that 100% of the kids are going to continue to participate.   Based on what I&rsquo;ve learned, I&rsquo;m working on some changes that I think will make the experience better.  Stay tuned, I&rsquo;ll announce those next week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clones and variables - Coding Class Week 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/clones-and-variables-coding-class-week-6/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-06T08:58:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/clones-and-variables-coding-class-week-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week was a bit of a stretch.  I wanted to teach the kids about clones.  This is a concept that&rsquo;s used fairly extensively in video games.</p>

<h2>Video</h2>

<p>We watched this video &ndash; someone basically modeled minecraft in a 3D toolkit.  I wanted them to see clones and physics in action.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/o702In0aI5E" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>Clones</h2>

<p><img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/clones.jpg" alt="Clones" /></p>

<p>Clones are copies of things.  The kids have been learning to make a game, but the games tend to have very few characters, and they have to script them out individually.  This can be tedious and still feel fairly manual.</p>

<p>Part of the magic of coding is when you start building lots of objects that interact with each other.   Much of this involves math and physics, so that you can simulate bouncing, gravity, and other real world phenomena.</p>

<p>However, I figured that the kids would be far enough along that they could try.</p>

<h2>Shoot the Penguin</h2>

<p><img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/shoot-the-penguin.png" alt="Shoot the penguin" /></p>

<p>We were going to make a simple game  &ndash; I just called it &ldquo;Shoot the Penguin&rdquo;.  Make a gun, make a bullet, make a penguin.   If the bullet touches the penguin, the penguin dies.</p>

<p>I gave them an example of a gun that shoots a bullet.  Some of the kids had previously figured out how to do this; They had a gun sprite and a bullet sprite and when they hit the space bar, the bullet sprite started moving until it hit the edge.</p>

<h2>Direction, Position, and Variables</h2>

<p>At some point, most of the kids had figured out how to make the gun shoot a bullet, and even kill the penguin.</p>

<p>Then, the next goal was to aim the gun.   This was useful because the kids naturally start complaining that their gun doesn&rsquo;t work too well, since it won&rsquo;t aim, and the bullet sometimes doesn&rsquo;t shoot out of the gun.  So, we had to create some global variables to store the position of the gun, and then copy those to the bullet so that the bullet knew which direction to go.</p>

<h2>Scratch Limitations, and Bugs</h2>

<p>Scratch is very &ldquo;opionated&rdquo;, and only comes with a subset of features available in modern programming languages.  It&rsquo;d be better if it was more object oriented, such that I could query the gun&rsquo;s position, instead of copying into a global variable.  This would have been more natural for the kids to understand.  Copying around variables around is a little bit confusing and messy.</p>

<p>We also ran into some bugs &ndash; sprites would just simply not rotate correctly sometimes, and we had to delete them and re-add them.  It was also common for kids to build a complicated sprite, but put it in the wrong place (ie, as a backdrop or as a costume attached to a different sprite)  When they finally realized they did it wrong, they had no idea how to move it.</p>

<p>We finally figured out that you do it by downloading the sprite to your local computer, then uploading again.  Copy/paste would have been better.</p>

<p>Also, renaming variables and sprites tends to break script blocks, which don&rsquo;t update their references always.  So, either name your variables and sprites up front, or don&rsquo;t bother.</p>

<h2>Next Week</h2>

<p>I keep meaning to let the kids just build in class, and not really teach them anything.  I think for the last 2 weeks, that&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;ll do.  They can be creative, and I&rsquo;ll just help them as they finish their &ldquo;final projects&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Keep your ASP.NET MVC projects organized with partial classes]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/keep-your-asp-dot-net-mvc-projects-more-organized-with-partial-classes/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-01T10:57:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/keep-your-asp-dot-net-mvc-projects-more-organized-with-partial-classes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I use partial classes for controller and service classes to keep my ASP.NET MVC projects more organized.</p>

<h3>The default behavior (file-per-controller) creates large files with lots of methods</h3>

<p>I&rsquo;ve built many projects that use the standard Visual Studio csproj template, which creates a file per controller.  Over time, a controller may accumulate many methods (tens or even hundreds)</p>

<p>This makes these files difficult to read and navigate.
<img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/messy-controller.png" alt="messy controller" /></p>

<h2>Controllers</h2>

<h3>Store ViewModels in the same file as controller methods</h3>

<p>ViewModels are coupled to a controller and a view.</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/7739637.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>using System;
using System.Collections.Generic;
using System.Linq;
using System.Web;
using System.Web.Mvc;
namespace BetterMvc.Controllers.Home
{
    public partial class HomeController : ControllerBase
    {
        public ActionResult Index()
        {
            var result = svc.DoSomething(new Services.Master.DoSomethingRequest
            {
            });
            var vm = new IndexViewModel { };
            return View(vm);
        }
    }

    public class IndexViewModel
    {
        public string UserName {get;set;}

    }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>


<h2>WebAPI</h2>

<h3>Store GET/POST/DELETE/PUT methods in the different files</h3>

<p>When using WebAPI, you will have multiple methods that apply to the same resource, for saving, deleting, updating, etc.</p>

<p>Each of these methods will have a different view model and controller action.</p>

<p>Create a directory with the name of the controller, and create each WebAPI controller as a partial.</p>

<p>Store each WebAPI action in a separate file, along with it&rsquo;s associated ViewModel.</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/7752207.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>using System;
using System.Collections.Generic;
using System.Linq;
using System.Web;
using System.Web.Http;

namespace BetterMvc.Api.V1.User
{
    public class GetUser
    {
    [HttpGet]
    public GetUserViewModel Get()
        {
            return new GetUserViewModel();
        }
    }

    public class GetUserViewModel
    {
        public string Username { get; set; }
        public string ImageUrl { get; set; }

    }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>


<h2>Services</h2>

<h3>Store DTOs in the same file as service methods</h3>

<p>In a Request/Response pattern, DTOs are coupled to service methods.</p>

<p>By storing the request and response in the same file, it is easier to make changes.</p>

<h3>Store interface definitions in the same file as service methods</h3>

<p>If you use a Dependency Injection Framework (such as <a href="http://www.ninject.org">Ninject</a>), you will have an interface definition for each public service method.  This creates file navigation problems with a typical ASP.NET MVC project, since hitting F12 on a method call from a controller will land you on the interface definition, as opposed to the method implementation.</p>

<p>By putting the interface definition in the same file as the primary method definition, you can simply scroll down the page to implementation.  You can also use a tool like <a href="http://www.jetbrains.com/resharper/">ReSharper</a>, but I find that workflow to require more navigation than simply housing these files together.</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/7752306.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>using System;
using System.Collections.Generic;
using System.Linq;
using System.Web;

namespace BetterMvc.Services.Master
{
    public partial interface IMasterService
    {
        DoSomethingResult DoSomething(DoSomethingRequest request);
    }

    public partial class MasterService : IMasterService
    {
        public DoSomethingResult DoSomething(DoSomethingRequest request)
        {
            return new DoSomethingResult { SomeData = &quot;foo&quot; };
        }
    }

    public class DoSomethingResult : Result
    {
        public string SomeData { get; set; }

    }

    public class DoSomethingRequest : Request
    {
        public int Id { get; set; }

    }
}</code></pre></noscript></div>


<h2>Version Control and Code Review</h2>

<h3>Use shell commands to navigate files</h3>

<p>Shell commands (powershell, dos, bash) become much more powerful when your code is organized by granularly by files.</p>

<ul>
<li>Sort by alpha, date modified, size changes</li>
<li>Use git status / hg st to find which sections of code changed</li>
</ul>


<h3>Reduce Merge Conflicts by organizing files more granularly</h3>

<p>The bane of a developers existence is a merge conflict.   In common workflows, a team of developers often work on one feature of the code at a time, and teams try to make an effort not to work on the same &ldquo;area&rdquo;.</p>

<p>When different areas of code are combined into one file, merge conflicts arise.</p>

<p>In ASP.NET MVC, this means you may be working on a few controller method, views, and service methods to implement a new feature.</p>

<p>By reducing the size of files you are working on, and keeping them organized by subject, it is less likely that you will have conflicts with other developers.  Or, you may only have them in the .csproj file, where it is fairly trivial and safe to resolve.</p>

<h3>Make Code Reviews easier to Read</h3>

<p>If you use git or mercurial for source control, you will often do code reviews by reviewing a branch of code(ie., feature-branch), and comparing it to another branch (ie, develop).</p>

<p>When doing these comparisons, you will see a series of commits that are grouped by file.  If associated assets (DTOs or ViewModels) reside in the same file as the methods that they support, it is easier to review, since you don&rsquo;t have to jump around as much.</p>

<p>You can also quickly scan filenames to understand the subject of the change.</p>

<p><img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/github-diff.png" alt="github diff" /></p>

<h3>Better MVC</h3>

<p>I am organizing these practices into a project on Github, humbly called <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/BetterMVC">BetterMVC</a>.</p>

<p>My goal is to make BetterMVC a lightweight project template that allows you to start new MVC projects in a clean way, and adopt some best practices along the way.  Right now, it is simply more of a reference.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/tarr11/BetterMVC">Fork BetterMVC Here</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratch Variables and Lists - Coding Class Week 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/scratch-variables-and-lists-coding-class-week-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-27T13:44:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/scratch-variables-and-lists-coding-class-week-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week we learned about variables and lists.</p>

<h2>How Computers Work</h2>

<p>We watched this Ted video on how computers work.  I&rsquo;m not sure any of it sunk in, but it was a good way to visualize how a computer processes things.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/AkFi90lZmXA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>Keeping Score</h2>

<p>Rather than present variables as an abstract concept, I asked the kids if they wanted to keep score in their games.  Most of them did, a few weren&rsquo;t sure.</p>

<p>So, we made a game this week where we made a map, animated a sprite, and collected coins, which would increase their score.</p>

<p>Once their score got a certain point, they would win.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example from one of the students
<img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/coin-game.png" alt="Coin Game" /></p>

<h2>Math, Physics, Art, and Communication</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve noticed that the kids have to quickly learn a lot of advanced concepts in order to make their game work.  For example, they have to understand negative numbers, multiplication, and graphs.</p>

<p>They inevitably start to make fairly complex designs, and they have to learn how to keep things organized and modular.</p>

<p>Several kids have wanted to make their character &ldquo;jump&rdquo;, which involves simulating physics (gravity, velocity, etc)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s pretty amazing what they will learn quickly enough if they are motivated.</p>

<p>My sense is that programming games is a great way to teach just about any subject at this age.  They have to quickly master a concept and if they don&rsquo;t, their program won&rsquo;t work.</p>

<h2>Finishing our game</h2>

<p>At this point, the kids may not know it, but they&rsquo;ve got a completely working game!  We will spend the remaining few weeks fine tuning our games and adding more features.</p>

<h2>Code Club HQ</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve rented a space for Code Club Headquarters, at 38 Miller Ave in Mill Valley.  I&rsquo;m very excited to put some cool stuff in there and run a few more classes.</p>

<p>Follow along here on this blog and <a href="http://facebook.com/mvcodeclub">become a fan on Facebook</a></p>

<p>If you live in Marin and are interested in having your child participate, please <a href="http://www.mvcodeclub.com/home/winterschedule">check out the schedule</a> on the <a href="http://www.mvcodeclub.com">mvcodeclub.com website</a></p>

<h2>Github</h2>

<p>As always, this class is available on <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-5.md">Github</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing New Relic on Elastic Beanstalk for Windows and IIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/installing-new-relic-on-elastic-beanstalk-for-windows-and-iis/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/installing-new-relic-on-elastic-beanstalk-for-windows-and-iis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had the experience of getting New Relic to install on an AWS Elastic Beanstalk environment using IIS and Windows.</p>

<p>There are some great tools that make this dead simple on Azure, but on Elastic Beanstalk, it&rsquo;s not quite as simple.   You can&rsquo;t just install using an MSI manually, since Elastic Beanstalk will auto-scale instances.</p>

<p>This means that you need to build it as part of the Elastic Beanstalk configuration.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create a directory called <code>.ebextensions</code> under the root of your project</li>
<li>Create a file called <code>newrelic.config</code> in that directory.  This will be in YAML format (2 spaces per indent)</li>
<li>Make sure to add this file to your .csproj project and include it as content so it copies up with AWS.</li>
<li>Download the latest <a href="https://docs.newrelic.com/docs/dotnet/new-relic-net-installation">.NET MSI from New Relic</a></li>
<li>Upload this MSI to S3 and make it public (everyone should be able to download it)</li>
<li>Get your New Relic license key from your New Relic account</li>
<li>In newrelic.config, copy this in:</li>
</ul>


<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>files:
</span><span class='line'>  "c:\\newrelic\\newrelic.msi":
</span><span class='line'>    source: [Your S3 URL]
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>commands:
</span><span class='line'>  install_newrelic:
</span><span class='line'>    command: msiexec.exe /i c:\\newrelic\\newrelic.msi NR_LICENSE_KEY=[Your License Key] INSTALLLEVEL=1</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<ul>
<li>This should copy down the MSI from your s3 bucket and install new relic with our license key to your instance</li>
<li>New Relic should start reporting your instances (called AMAZON-something)</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Messages and Animation - Coding Class Week 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/messages-and-animation-coding-class-week-4/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-21T08:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/messages-and-animation-coding-class-week-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The past 3 weeks, the kids have been learning a lot of things.  How to interact with Scratch, basic programming concepts, and some basic computer skills.</p>

<p>This week, we spent a little time learning something new (events and message passing) but most of the time, I wanted the kids to be focused on building something.</p>

<h2>Unity Video</h2>

<p>We watched this short time lapse video of someone building a game scene in Unity 3D. This looks more like the games that they play on consoles at home.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/Z2ZX9soqOz4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>Message Passing</h2>

<p>Our goal this week was for the kids to learn about how to animate a story.  The tools in Scratch for doing this are pretty light &ndash; they don&rsquo;t really support a timeline UI for keyframing, so there&rsquo;s a lot of manual counting going on in order to synchronize your characters.</p>

<p>I wanted to teach them about message passing, which is a powerful concept that lets them control their animations via events, as opposed to trying to coordinate timing.</p>

<h2>Animation Challenge</h2>

<p>I presented the kids with a challenge &ndash; they had to animate a story, but they were only allowed to press one button to start it, and then it needed to run on its own (sort of like tipping over dominoes)
<img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/dominoes.jpg" alt="Dominoes" /></p>

<p>They had gotten comfortable with event based processing, where they were controlling the animation sort of like a puppet show.  ie., press &ldquo;j&rdquo; and a character will jump.  I wanted them to use messages to instead say &ldquo;when this sprite is finished, it broadcasts a message&rdquo;.  And then, another sprite would listen for that</p>

<p>They spent much of the class working in teams of two, coming up with a story and then trying to animate it.  I liked this model because they would learn based on what they needed, as opposed to just going through and learning every command in the platform.</p>

<p>They loved to record sounds and have their characters do things together.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example of one of the animations (based on Pokemon) the kids put together:</p>

<iframe allowtransparency="true" width="485" height="402" src="http://scratch.mit.edu/projects/embed/14440381/?autostart=false" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Pretty impressive for some 4th graders who did this in about an hour!</p>

<h2>Computers, Creativity, Collaboration and Communication</h2>

<p>I spent some time thinking about the the role of a computer in the creative process.  There is a danger that because computers are powerful devices, they can have a hypnotic effect on the kids.</p>

<p>I wanted the kids to think about what they wanted to build, instead of just clicking around the computer.  This is an important skill for them to learn &ndash; these are just tools and they need to use the tools, not have the tools use them.</p>

<p>So, they spent a few minutes discussing what they wanted to build.  This was somewhat challenging and overwhelming.  A lot of them just wanted to mess around and build it that way.  I think that&rsquo;s fine, but I also wanted them to have their own point of view.</p>

<p>Some of the kids have more experience than others, and I wanted them to learn how to work together and teach each other.  If they are just working alone, they might as well be at home!  So, I spend some time each class trying to get them to work together, communicate, and solve problems together.  Since I&rsquo;ve put them on time limits for this project, that can be somewhat stressful.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good skill for them to learn how to manage their time and their communication under time pressure.</p>

<h2>Advanced Class + Another Intro Class In January</h2>

<p>We are going to have an advanced class starting in January.  I think it still will be focused around Scratch &ndash; there is a lot to learn here and I&rsquo;d like them to get a bit more mastery before we move on to more complex topics.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also thinking about running another Intro class &ndash; this is for 4th graders, but it could also work for 3rd and 5th graders as well.  I&rsquo;m hoping to include more girls as well, to balance things out.</p>

<p>If you are interested, please <a href="http://douglastarr.com/contact.html">contact me</a></p>

<h2>Mill Valley Code Club Website, Facebook, and HQ</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve finally got a the <a href="http://www.mvcodeclub.com">Mill Valley Code Club Website</a> setup.  This is where the kids log in, keep notes, and learn about new lessons.  I&rsquo;ll probably improve it more over time.</p>

<p>Also, I&rsquo;ve setup a <a href="http://www.facebook.com/mvcodeclub">Facebook Page</a> and a <a href="http://twitter.com/mvcodeclub">Twitter</a> if you are interested in following along.</p>

<h2>Code Club HQ?</h2>

<p>I am looking at renting out a small space in downtown Mill Valley, to run Code Club classes.  We&rsquo;ve been running out of my house which has been fine, but things get a little hectic, and there&rsquo;s a lot of setup and teardown that I have to do in our living room.</p>

<p>If we have a space, I can add some better hardware.  I have my eye on a <a href="http://www.makerbot.com">Makerbot</a> for example, which would be a fun thing for the kids to play with.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll probably also get a server that we can run Minecraft on, and a bunch of other fun stuff like <a href="http://arduino.cc">Arduino</a>, <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org">Raspberry Pi</a> etc.</p>

<h2>Github</h2>

<p>As always, <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-4.md">this weeks lesson plan</a> is on Github.  Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drawing and Painting - Coding Class Week 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/drawing-and-painting-coding-class-week-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T08:52:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/drawing-and-painting-coding-class-week-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Originally, my plan for this week was to run a series of Scratch Challenges (make an animated story, a maze, etc).</p>

<p> I had Eli try one out, and I quickly realized that a lot of time is spent on creating sprites.  So, I decided to completely focus the class on drawing and painting.</p>

<p>To start the class, we watched this timelapse video of someone making a game character in Illustrator.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/k2xYSCNysS0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This gave the kids an idea of what is possible.  Timelapse videos have a &ldquo;magic&rdquo; to them and I noticed that the kids were mesmerized by it.  They were certainly still chatting and joking (&ldquo;hey that kind of looks like the guy who works at Jamba Juice!&rdquo;) but they were paying attention.</p>

<h2>Drawing and Painting Happy Faces in Scratch</h2>

<p>It turns out that Scratch comes with a fairly decent draw/paint tool.  It&rsquo;s like a simplified version of Adobe Illustrator / Photoshop.</p>

<p>When presented with a drawing or painting tool online, kids immediately just go for a paintbrush and predictably have a hard time making something look good.</p>

<p>Pictures of faces tend to look like very messy.  I had the kids go through and try to make &ldquo;better&rdquo; happy faces so that they could understand why it&rsquo;s better to use vector based methods for drawing instead of bitmap methods.</p>

<p>My goal for the class was to get them to understand what the tools (especially the vector tools) do so that they could make and remix existing vector illustrations.</p>

<p>We learned about painting (bitmaps) and drawing (vectors) and what you could do with each.</p>

<p><img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/animation.gif" alt="Happy Face Progression" /></p>

<p>We learned how to make shapes, fill them in, resize and reshape them.  We also learned how to group and ungroup shapes in vector mode, and the difference between resizing shapes in bitmap vs vector.</p>

<h2>Remixing</h2>

<p>The &ldquo;a-ha&rdquo; moment of the class was then they realized that they could go to the Scratch sprite library, grab a vector based sprite, and then &ldquo;re-mix&rdquo; it to their needs.
<img src="http://douglastarr.com/images/gobo-anim.gif" alt="Gobo" /></p>

<p>We had about 5 or 10 minutes at the end &ndash; I asked the kids to try and make a few drawings and see if they could animate them (using what they learned from last week)  A few of them (who were more comfortable) were able to do this.  Most had a hard time recalling how to connect these two things.</p>

<h2>Speed, Focus and Fun</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re still having some challenges around getting everyone to focus.  I find myself having to use &ldquo;teacher-voice&rdquo; more than I&rsquo;d like.  I could see some yawns at the beginning of class after a hard day at school.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also noticed that sometimes, the kids just are in there, doing their own thing, and not totally paying attention to what I&rsquo;m having them learn.  That&rsquo;s ok (that&rsquo;s exactly how I was as a kid their age), but I try to go around and make sure everyone gets the gist of the lesson.</p>

<p>And then there was this&hellip;</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>OH in <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23mvcodeclub&amp;src=hash">#mvcodeclub</a> yesterday - &quot;OOOOH, If I make the boogers into sprites, I can make them drip down the squirrel&#39;s nose!&quot;</p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/400341894791589888">November 12, 2013</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://douglastarr.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>We are literally blazing through Scratch in a really short time.  These kids are learning a lot quickly, but that does lead to some frustration when they don&rsquo;t pick something up as quickly as they&rsquo;d like.</p>

<p>I can sometimes see some frustration when it takes a little longer than they had hoped to figure something out.  It&rsquo;s ok if they don&rsquo;t &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; a skill before moving on to the next one.  I can sense that some of them want to spend more time before moving on.</p>

<p>That said, it seems like everyone is having a great time.</p>

<h2>Next Week</h2>

<p>Next week we are going to work together on teams.  We&rsquo;ll use some of the lessons that we learned to do some challenges together.</p>

<h2>Github</h2>

<p>As always, this lesson is available on Github here &ndash; <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-3.md">Lesson 3 on Github</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A call to application developers - the cloud needs to go]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/a-call-to-application-developers-the-cloud-needs-to-go/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-09T08:31:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/a-call-to-application-developers-the-cloud-needs-to-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As software proliferates, customers have more and more choices as to where they put their data.  Why would they choose your service?  As software developers, we think that this is mostly an issue of feature parity.  But there are other factors that go into the decision &ndash; business relationships, price, and most relevant to this article, trust.</p>

<h2>Trust as a Service</h2>

<p>Multi-Tenant cloud services are problematic and insecure.  We need a new solution for cloud computing that allows more security and better resource management.</p>

<p>There are many examples of single-tenant architectures, but they are usually reserved for use cases where compliance is required (ie., health care and finance).</p>

<p>In these cases,  single tenancy is not always really enforced; There is often a separate database instance that is running for each customer, but the instances are on a shared server, and many other resources (application servers, search, network) are shared.</p>

<p>On the flipside, many line-of-business or backoffice apps are single tenant applications, since they are by definition only run by one client.</p>

<p>The movement towards instances has been growing as IaaS has proliferated (AWS, Azure, etc), and tools like <a href="http://docker.io">docker</a> and <a href="http://bitnami.com">bitnami</a> make it easier to spin up isolated instances, but the developer software platform support is minimal or non-existent.</p>

<h2>The problems with cloud</h2>

<p>There are many problems with cloud services:</p>

<ul>
<li>Customer data is intermingled</li>
<li>You are paying for scale that you simply don&rsquo;t need</li>
<li>SaaS databases are a rich target for criminals, extortion and spying.</li>
<li>Data security is a secondary consideration, or not well enforced inside SaaS company</li>
</ul>


<h3>Intermingled Data and Resources</h3>

<p>As a SaaS customer, have you ever stopped to ask why your resources are intermingled with other customers?  The reason is simply that software companies are not equipped to isolate your data.  This would require complete rewrites of code, as well as an order of magnitude more ops support.</p>

<p>In short, it&rsquo;s prohibitively expensive to isolate your data, given the software infrastructure currently available.</p>

<h3>Security issues abound</h3>

<p>A common SaaS application stack looks like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Application Server (Rails, Django, etc)</li>
<li>Search Engine (Elastic Search / SOLR, etc)</li>
<li>Database (Postgres, MySql, etc)</li>
<li>A myriad of cloud solutions for logging, email, alerts, backups, analytics</li>
</ul>


<p>Each of these components has an opportunity for security issues.  Many developers have access to your application server.  Your search engine or database may be hosted by a third party service.   The cloud solutions you are using proliferate customer data across hundreds or thousands of different environments.</p>

<p>Each one of these layers offers spying entities an opportunity to access your data.</p>

<h3>Wasteful Scale problems</h3>

<p>Most SaaS applications are built on a relational SQL environment.  All customer data is stored in the same table, and separated by foreign keys.</p>

<p>This means that if another customer puts a high demand on a resource (typically a database instance) that also houses your data, access to your data may be impacted, and you may experience performance issues when using the SaaS application.</p>

<p>Developers spend huge amounts of time on this problem.  High Scalability has gone from a niche area of Computer Science to something that is asked as part of a junior software engineer interview.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also incredibly hard to get right.</p>

<p>Scale should be a problem for infrastructure platforms, not applications platforms.  Trying to address scale in an application is fraught with problems and tremendously expensive.</p>

<p>If SaaS moved to a single instance architecture, we could push these scale problems down the stack to a few IaaS providers.  Your application simply has to be able to scale to one organization, not all the potential customers you might have.  This can change your development cycle significantly.</p>

<p>We could also provide meaningful SLAs to customers since we could isolate their resources and pass on the SLA offered by IaaS such as AWS.</p>

<h2>Let&rsquo;s build a Single Instance Stack</h2>

<p>Given how hard it is to isolate your data, it makes sense that so few SaaS providers offer it.  There are simply few resources, developers or stacks that can help support it.  The IT / devops requirements are too burdensome.</p>

<p>But, it&rsquo;s certainly possible!  After all, this is how IaaS providers work.  They can monitor and provision your application and guarantee a certain number of 9&rsquo;s of uptime.  Your SaaS should do the same, and your customers shouldn&rsquo;t have to hire a devops pro to run your cloud.</p>

<h3>It&rsquo;s not just about OSS</h3>

<p>Much open source software works in this way.  Simply download the software and run it on your own infrastructure.</p>

<p>Single Tenant software is not a new concept.  It&rsquo;s what everyone did before they went to cloud solutions.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s still a common model for certain kinds of enterprise software (ie, MSFT) and Open Source software.</p>

<p>However, the problem is that it requires a deep level of IT expertise that is prohibitive.</p>

<h2>A Single Tenant Ruby on Rails?</h2>

<p>We need an application stack for Isolated Environments.  We need a stack like Rails, that enables developers to easily build single tenant solutions.</p>

<p>Ie, instead of deploying your SaaS app to one Heroku or AWS instance, you deploy it to 5000.</p>

<p>If you have worked on any SaaS application, just thinking about that is probably enough to give you a migraine.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s missing?   Basically all backoffice support that allows you to manage thousands of customer environments.</p>

<p>This is an incredibly hard task &ndash; just thinking about running a database migration on thousands of instances of customer databases makes my head spin.</p>

<p>Think about all the components of your current SaaS app &ndash; and now try and figure out how to manage them across thousands of instances.  I suspect this would require some sort of management API that can deploy code, upgrades, and let you remotely manage data.</p>

<ul>
<li>Robust Security Model</li>
<li>Managing Users-</li>
<li>Pluggable Service Components</li>
<li>Supporting Deployments</li>
<li>DevOps and Provisioning</li>
<li>Migrations, Versioning and Upgrades</li>
</ul>


<p>I suspect that some of these components are out there.</p>

<p>Perhaps they just need to be assembled into a stack that is more manageable.</p>

<p>Perhaps they don&rsquo;t exist.</p>

<p>Do we need this stack?  Please share your thoughts in comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Intro to Scratch - Coding Class Week 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/intro-to-scratch-coding-class-week-2/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-08T09:03:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/intro-to-scratch-coding-class-week-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was the second week of my <a href="http://douglastarr.com/categories/mvcoders">8 Week Coding Class for 4th Graders</a></p>

<p>This class started a bit more chaotic than the <a href="http://douglastarr.com/coding-class-week-1/">first week</a>.</p>

<h2>Code Club Philosophy</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m not really teaching a class, I&rsquo;m <a href="http://douglastarr.com/3-types-of-programming-classes-for-kids/">running a club</a>, and I don&rsquo;t really care if they learn computer science fundamentals.</p>

<p>I want the kids to:</p>

<ul>
<li>have fun</li>
<li>build things</li>
</ul>


<p>If those two things happen, they&rsquo;ll naturally be more interested.  If they get &ldquo;hooked&rdquo;, they&rsquo;ll be more motiviated to learn more complicated computer science topics.</p>

<h3>Don&rsquo;t worry about how it works.  Just go.</h3>

<p>When learning to drive a car, the focus is on getting the car from point A to point B.</p>

<p>You don&rsquo;t need to know how to use the defroster, how the automatic transmission functions, or the biography of Enzo Ferrari.</p>

<p>And, unlike a car, it&rsquo;s ok if you write some code and it immediately crashes.</p>

<p>So, I&rsquo;m running the class by giving them the keys and letting them drive.  They&rsquo;ll figure out how things work later.</p>

<p>I can tell there is a tremendous sense of empowerment and joy when they realize that they get to do what they want.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a bit chaotic at first, as they start honking the horn, gunning the engine, and laughing uncontrollably.</p>

<p>Fortunately, they don&rsquo;t get into any major accidents.</p>

<h2>Chat</h2>

<p>For one of the classes, I wired up a chat program using <a href="http://togetherjs.com">TogetherJs</a>  The kids LOVED it, but it was big mistake.  As soon as they saw a chat window, they went crazy chatting with each other and paid no attention to me.  TogetherJs is also not just a simple chat program &ndash; it lets each kid control other screens.</p>

<p>As you can imagine&hellip; this didn&rsquo;t work out so well.</p>

<p>It took me about 10 minutes to reel them back in.  I think chat is a valuable tool, but I&rsquo;ll need to rethink how I can use it.</p>

<h2>12 year old app developer</h2>

<p>We watched <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Fkd9TWUtFm0">this video about a 12 year old app developer</a>.  The kids <em>kind of</em> liked it, but I think the reception was kind of muted.  We need better videos.</p>

<p>If you know of short videos that might appeal to kids to learn code, please share them in the comments.</p>

<h2>Learning about Loops and Commands</h2>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t really want to spend a lot of time talking, maybe 5 or 10 minutes at most.  It is really hard to have a conversation with them when there are laptops sitting in front of them.</p>

<p>We talked a little bit about loops, commands and programs, and how they fit together.</p>

<p>These kids are all fantastic students.  I can tell that they are all pretty well behaved in the classroom, and they respond to &ldquo;classroom-like&rdquo;&ldquo; questions pretty well.</p>

<p>I think it&rsquo;s important to have them talk for a few minutes, if only to get them calmed down and thinking about computers.</p>

<h2>Learning Scratch</h2>

<p>This week, we started to use <a href="http://scratch.mit.edu">MIT Scratch</a> which is a visual programming environment with a rich curriculum, geared towards children.</p>

<p><img src="http://scratchdaysiegen.files.wordpress.com/2011/12/scratch-cat.jpg" alt="Scratch Logo" /></p>

<p>I decided to run this class mostly by following the <a href="http://cdn.scratch.mit.edu/scratchr2/static/__1383932368__//pdfs/help/Getting-Started-Guide-Scratch2.pdf">Getting Started</a> intro on the Scratch website.</p>

<p>The Getting Started Tutorial teaches them how to:</p>

<ul>
<li>move a sprite around</li>
<li>manipulate &ldquo;code blocks&rdquo;</li>
<li>use a &ldquo;repeat&rdquo; control block</li>
<li>change sprite colors</li>
<li>make sounds</li>
<li>change backgrounds</li>
<li>response to some basic user input.</li>
</ul>


<p>I had wanted to get further, but it was clear that this was how far we were going to get.</p>

<p>Since some of the kids had &ldquo;played&rdquo; with Scratch before, I let them go faster, so they wouldn&rsquo;t be bored.</p>

<h2>Tips and Tricks</h2>

<ul>
<li>Kids should have a mouse. It&rsquo;s really hard to manipulate Scratch with a touchpad.</li>
<li>If some kids get too far ahead, use them as teaching assistants to help the other kids

<ul>
<li>This helps the further ahead kids since they have to explain what they are doing and will learn more.</li>
<li>It helps the other kids catch up.</li>
<li>And it helps me keep control of the class.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Windows 8 is kind of difficult for kids to use.  There are lots of weird swipes that cause the tile screen to show up.</li>
<li>Chromebooks are actually fine.</li>
<li>If you are teaching kids Scratch, these are the things that tripped them up:

<ul>
<li>Separating Blocks and Removing them</li>
<li>Their sprites would fall off the screen, and we had to figure out how to get them back.</li>
<li>They&rsquo;d add some new sprites to the screen and they couldn&rsquo;t figure out how to delete them</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>By 4th grade, they are all pretty adept at finding videos and images on YouTube.</li>
<li>At the end of the class, I have them type up some notes about what they learned and save them with each lesson.  This helps them think about what they accomplished.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Stories from the kids</h2>

<p>A few kids had used Scratch before and had some &ldquo;tricks&rdquo; up their sleeves.  I saw a few memes I recognized from Reddit.</p>

<p>One of the students in the class learned how to make animations by stringing three drawings together and rotating through them.  Pretty amazing.</p>

<p>A few kids were a little disappointed that we weren&rsquo;t doing CodeCombat again in class.</p>

<h2>On Github</h2>

<p>As with the <a href="http://douglastarr.com/an-open-source-coding-curriculum/">rest of this class</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-2.md">This week&rsquo;s curriculum</a> is available on Github.</p>

<h2>Next Week</h2>

<p>Next week the kids are going to team up into groups of 2 and I&rsquo;m going to give them a few challenges using the skills that they learned, and maybe one or two new ones.</p>

<h2>Suggestions and Resources</h2>

<p>If you have any suggestions for the class, or resources to share, please do so in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coding Class Week 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/coding-class-week-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T09:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/coding-class-week-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was the first week of my <a href="http://douglastarr.com/categories/mvcoders">8 Week Coding Class for 4th Graders</a></p>

<p>I ran 2 classes after school (about 5 kids per class) after school.  I was a bit nervous to get started as I had no idea what was going to happen, or if the kids were going to get bored.  We followed the plan that I laid out in my <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-1.md">the fourth grade coding curriculum</a> on Github, with a few modifications.</p>

<h2>After school</h2>

<p>Getting everyone to focus at the beginning was tough.  They came directly from school and were a little bit rambunctious from sitting in class all day.  Some kids immediately booted up their laptops to play a video game and I had to tell them not to.</p>

<h2>Computers</h2>

<p>I asked the kids to bring their own laptops if possible.  I have a series of old laptops and fortunately, most of them worked, even if they were a little bit slow.   I needed Google Chrome installed on each computer, which I had to install on a few of their laptops.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to avoid using any native shell programs since they aren&rsquo;t going to be the same amongst all the laptops that the kids have.  For example, I&rsquo;ve had kids bring Macbooks, Chromebooks and Windows 7 and 8 laptops.  Even trying to get a <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/bash/">bash shell</a> running on all those environments would have been tough.</p>

<p>In the future, I may look at <a href="http://nitrous.io">Nitrous.io</a> if I do want a terminal that they can all use.  I tried out making a &ldquo;Hello World&rdquo; <a href="http://voxeljs.com">Voxel.js</a> / <a href="http://nodejs.org">Node.js</a> with Nitrous, and that worked.  I may use that in a future class, to show them how you can code your own Minecraft world.</p>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>I asked the kids what they thought programming was.  Some named programming languages like HTML.  One mentioned &ldquo;The Matrix&rdquo; and how they used progrmaming there. A few said Minecraft.  Some said it was a way to get computers to do what you want.  A few had no idea.</p>

<p>I asked them what they wanted to do in the class?  In the first class, they all unanimously said &ldquo;make video games&rdquo;.  Some had very specific ideas about the games that they wanted to make.  In the second class, it was a mix.  One wanted to make a very specific Minecraft plugin that made it easy and safe to make other Minecraft plugins.  One wanted to make it safer to use computers online (he was on a Windows 8 laptop, FWIW).  The rest wanted to make video games.</p>

<p>They responded well (&ldquo;woohoo!&rdquo;) when I told them that this wasn&rsquo;t going to be like a normal class in school where you had to listen to a teacher talk, and that they&rsquo;d spend a lot of time coding.  That said, I did have to calm them down periodically, just like any class.</p>

<h2>ChromeCast</h2>

<p>The class was in our living room, and I used my laptop + <a href="http://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/devices/chromecast/">ChromeCast</a> to show them videos and code samples on the screen.  This worked out really well &ndash; we watched the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nKIu9yen5nc">Code.org video</a> in one of the classes, and the kids responded really well to seeing Bill Gates and Mark Zuckerberg on the screen, talking about coding.</p>

<h2>CodeCombat</h2>

<p><img src="https://github-camo.global.ssl.fastly.net/5cbc6e9e49ea8cecd35303f9e62bf27cda4edefa/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f496c76373352382e706e67" alt="Code Combat Screenshot" /></p>

<p>A few weeks ago, on <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com">Hacker News</a>, I heard about a cool site called <a href="http://codecombat.com">CodeCombat</a> which teaches kids some javascript and coding fundamentals.  There are a series of &ldquo;challenges&rdquo; that the kids have to go through, such as having their knight defeat a troll, move around a maze, and say various things in order.   Overall &ndash; the kids LOVED this game and had a lot of fun.  I think they didn&rsquo;t even realize that they were learning coding.  I heard from one parent that their kid had a lot of fun but didn&rsquo;t learn much. I think this was because they thought they were just playing a game.  But in order to play the game, you have to write a lot of javascript, understand logic flow and how to construct and debug a sophisticated program.  So, I considered it a success because it was a lot of fun.</p>

<p>That said, running the class reminded me of the game <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diner_Dash">Diner Dash</a> for a while. In that game, you are a waitress, and your job is to take and serve complex orders in a diner very quickly.  If you mess up the orders or take too long, customers get mad.  If you do everything right, you get points. I found that with 5 or 6 kids, especially as they get going, they are hitting roadblocks about every minute.   Most of these involved some sort of debugging of their javascript code.  They would say &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not working&rdquo; and I&rsquo;d come over and try to help them figure out what&rsquo;s wrong.   If I spent too much time helping one student, the bugs would back up and I&rsquo;d have a lot of kids unhappy.  If the kids were blocked for too long, they would get frustrated.</p>

<p>One thing I am not sure about is how someone with no programming experience can help kids.  Most of the problems that I was solving for were debugging issues.  These are easy for developers to solve (sometimes) but sometimes they are not!  Some of these problems could be resolved with a more sophisticated user interface.  But making debugging &ldquo;easy&rdquo; is a famously hard problem in computer science.  One example of this problem is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halting_problem">halting problem</a>  Ie, trying to detect if a computer is stuck in an infinite loop.   I think this gets easier with visual programming languages since it&rsquo;s easier to stay &ldquo;on the rails&rdquo;.  But, much of the power of coding is still in language based coding, so I want to balance out these two techniques.</p>

<p>That said, whenever the kids solved a problem on their own (ie, fixed a missing parentheses, semicolon, or capitalization), they would get very excited that they accomplished something.  CodeCombat also did a good job of helping them celebrate their victories by showing them a little animation of their knight crushing the enemy or winning.</p>

<h2>Browser Based Coding</h2>

<p>CodeCombat uses two windows &ndash; a game and a javascript editor in a browser.  This does present some challenges.  The coding window loses focus a lot, and the kids expect when they start typing, sometimes nothing would happen.  The game would occasionally get stuck, or the browser would get wonky, and I&rsquo;d have to reset the screen.   At this age (9 + 10 years old), this would be a tough game for the kids to learn without my help.</p>

<p>The kids also needed to learn to type like a software developer would.  Learning how to type as a coder is different than typing words.  I am not teaching them to use advanced coding motions (ie, <a href="http://www.vim.org/">vim</a> ) but there are a set of things that they need to code javascript.  For example, they need to know various characters &ndash; parentheses, semicolon, single and double quotes.  They need to know how to position the cursor on a line and insert a new line below it.  They need to know how to &ldquo;pronounce&rdquo; code.  ie, when I asked them to pronounce &ldquo;this.moveNext();&rdquo;, they said &ldquo;this period move next parentheses parentheses semicolon&rdquo;.   Teaching them how &ldquo;talk in code&rdquo; was a surprising thing that was important to teach.</p>

<h2>CodeClub Software</h2>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-YV1ZHLB3uao/UnGDazlwlCI/AAAAAAAAYlE/K5tPI5iS5JM/w1623-h1217-no/20131030_150608.jpg" alt="CodeClub Software on ChromeCast" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve built a little ASP.NET MVC website that gives them logins, lets them take notes, and then guides them through the class using the curriculum that I put on Github.   This mostly worked, but there was a bug in the first class where some of their notes didn&rsquo;t save.   This software is really valuable for parents to see what&rsquo;s going on, and it gives me a way to communicate and guide the class.  This code isn&rsquo;t available yet but I plan to put it online in a few weeks.</p>

<h2>Second Class</h2>

<p>The goal of the next class is to introduce them to <a href="http://scratch.mit.edu">MIT Scratch</a> which is a visual environment for learning to make games and animations.  I&rsquo;m working on the curriculum now, so check back in a week or so to see how that went.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Open Source Coding Curriculum]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/an-open-source-coding-curriculum/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T11:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/an-open-source-coding-curriculum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://github.global.ssl.fastly.net/images/modules/training/professortocat.png" alt="Github Teacher Logo" /></p>

<p>One of the biggest challenges in teaching a coding class is the curriculum.  What are the kids going to do during each class?  How do we keep them challenged?  Is the class something that they enjoy, or not?</p>

<h2>Discovering Curriculums Online</h2>

<p>I have been feverishly searching the internet for a coding curriculum that works for an in-person coding class.  There are a lot of resources that are geared toward online classes, but very few for in person classes.</p>

<p>There are a lot of people thinking about this same problem right now.  Every day, I hear about parents and teachers trying to teach their kids to code, and going online to figure out how to do it.</p>

<h2>Coding Curriculum on GitHub</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m putting the <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons">curriculum I&rsquo;m building</a> on Github so that other parents and teachers can learn from it, or use it for their own needs.  <a href="https://github.com">Github</a> is a tool that is used by software developers to share and discover code.  But, it&rsquo;s also great for sharing and discovering any &ldquo;structured&rdquo; data.  Since I&rsquo;m using github, you can change the curriculum as you need for your own purposes (just sign up for a Github account and then click the &ldquo;Fork&rdquo; button on the project)</p>

<p>My curriculum is fairly straightforward &ndash; it&rsquo;s a way to guide me through an 90 minutes with 4 or 5 kids.  I&rsquo;ve decided to use GitHub to host the curriculum, and I&rsquo;m using a simple language called MarkDown to write the curriculum.  MarkDown is like HTML, but a bit easier to write.  For instance, you can just write text, with no formatting, and it&rsquo;s smart enough to make things format fairly nicely.  It also supports most of the basic web formats you&rsquo;d expect &ndash; images, links, etc.  It&rsquo;s a bit more technical than writing an email (since there are a few special codes) but if you are teaching a coding class, you probably won&rsquo;t mind a few more codes, right?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m writing the curriculum as I go, since I need to see how students respond to each class to structure the next one.  My best guess on how the class will go is available on Github.  You can &ldquo;star&rdquo; the repository on Github if you want to follow along as i change it.  You can also use the <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/issues">Issues feature</a> of Github to provide comments on the curriculum itself.  Finally, if you want to make your own curriculum, you can <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/fork">Fork it</a> and make your own.  There will be a lot of changes (until the end of December 2013) so beware if you are trying to stay &ldquo;in sync&rdquo; with me.</p>

<p>View the curriculum here:</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/tree/master/4th-grade-coders">4th Grade Coding Class on Github</a></h3>

<h2>CodeClub software</h2>

<p>A few months ago, it was Eli&rsquo;s birthday, and we invited his friends over to play MineCraft.  I brought out some of my old laptops, and some of the kids brought their own.  I tried to get everyone setup to play Minecraft on our network, and that took some time, even with just 8 or 10 kids.</p>

<p>What I learned from that experience was that even having some basic links and setup in a web browser can go a long way to making the class more effecient.</p>

<p>The kids I&rsquo;m working with don&rsquo;t all have email addresses &ndash; so I need a way to communicate with them as well, give them links, and give parents a way to follow what their kids are working on.</p>

<p>So, I&rsquo;ve decided to write some software called <a href="http://github.com/tarr11/codeclub">CodeClub</a> that lets you pull in any ccurriculum available on Github and use it to run your own class. The software will be free, open source, and MIT licensed.  Right now, that repository is blank since the code is pretty rough.</p>

<p>CodeClub is what we are going to be using in the class.  Once it&rsquo;s a little better, I&rsquo;ll put it up with some instructions on how you can easily host it yourself.</p>

<p>First class starts tomorrow, we are all very excited to get started.  Stay tuned on my blog to learn how it goes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 Types of Programming Classes for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/3-types-of-programming-classes-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-24T09:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/3-types-of-programming-classes-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing a lot of research on how to effectively make a curriculum for the 4th Graders that I am teaching.  Turns out, it&rsquo;s not easy!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been struggling to figure out what my role is in this experience.  For example, there are many <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course">MOOCs</a> (<a href="http://khanacademy.org">Khan Academy</a>, <a href="http://codeacademy.com">Code Academy</a> ) out there that essentially provide a self-directed learning environment.  There are some hybrid environments like <a href="http://tynker.com">Tynker</a> that provide a more structured environment which helps teachers run a larger class, but still get into some depth around programming.  It would be a waste of time for me to have them just simply turn on computers and point them at Khan Academy.</p>

<p>My experience watching my children try to use these tools is that they work well for everything &hellip; except programming.  It is really hard to make a perfectly self-contained, understandable, modular programming environment where the kids don&rsquo;t go off the rails.  That said &ndash; they are great to use when someone can help get past roadblocks, bugs in software, and design issues that make the software confusing. I think online or self-directed curricula are very important, but I think that if kids (especially younger kids) are left to their own on these programs, they will get stuck and discouraged, even with the best designed programs.</p>

<p>So, where does that leave us?  Can we adopt an online curriculum for our class or do we have to build our own?<br/>
There are some curricula out there, especially built around tools like <a href="http://scratch.mit.edu">MIT Scratch</a>.
The curriculum you use or develop is highly dependent on the kind of structure you put towards your class.  This stuff is probably pretty obvious to anyone who has been involved professionally in education (teachers, etc) but it&rsquo;s a new discovery for me.</p>

<p>I would categorize the curriculum into 3 groups (classes, teams, and clubs)</p>

<h2>The Class</h2>

<p>The entire class is going to be learning the exact same thing, at the same time.  This seems to be the model taken by schools.  It&rsquo;s also a valuable way to go if you have a large group of kids (more than 8 or 10) since you really won&rsquo;t have the time to give them individual attention.  You are trading some creativity and self-direction for scale.  It&rsquo;s also harder to get kids to be excited by a class.</p>

<h2>The Team</h2>

<p>You are teaching them some skills but there&rsquo;s a lot of free time and everyone need not learn the same thing.  There&rsquo;s a concept of working together as a team and collaborating.  Teams can be smaller, and different kids can specialize in different areas.  There&rsquo;s a sense of grouping by age and at the end of the &ldquo;season&rdquo; you should have learned some valuable skills.  You might have a competition or challenge as well.</p>

<h2>The Club</h2>

<p>You are there to provide some resources and keep everyone moving forward, but it&rsquo;s more self-directed.  My guess is that this model works really well in high school, where the kids have self-selected into wanting to participate and have the ability to solve more in depth problems on their own.  You are offering lots of opportunities and an environment for individual creativity and collaboration.</p>

<p>For the <a href="http://douglastarr.com/categories/mvcoders">MVCoders</a> group, I am going to use the &ldquo;Team&rdquo; approach since I am dealing with a small group of motivated kids.</p>

<h2>Future Questions To Address</h2>

<ul>
<li>Visual Programming Languages (ie, Scratch) vs Text based Languages (javascript)</li>
<li>What is an appropriate amount of &ldquo;help&rdquo; to give students</li>
<li>As a developer, how much custom code should I be writing myself?</li>
<li>What is the relationship of a coding class to other traditional classes?</li>
<li>What expectations does everyone (parents, kids, teachers, etc) have for the class?</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching Coding to 4th Graders]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/Teaching-Coding-to-4th-graders/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/Teaching-Coding-to-4th-graders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to teach coding to some 4th graders after school, including my son and about 7 other kids.</p>

<p>My background is as a software developer, but teaching is new to me.</p>

<p>So, I&rsquo;m planning on writing some blog entries to keep notes on what I&rsquo;ve learned and how I&rsquo;m structuring the class.  You can follow along about it using the <a href="http://douglastarr.com/categories/mvcoders">mvcoders</a> tag in my blog.</p>

<p>My son really enjoys Minecraft, to the point where he religiously watches every &ldquo;How-To&rdquo; video on YouTube about fun ways to use Redstone and Command Blocks to do neat things.</p>

<p>I really want to encourage kids to have fun programming.  It is so much different now and there are a ton of resources to use that don&rsquo;t require kids to get immersed in the guts of the OS to learn some basic coding.</p>

<p>My challenge has been to find a good curriculum to teach, and figure out how to best structure for the class so that all of the kids have a great experience.</p>

<p>Resources I&rsquo;m looking at using:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://scratch.mit.edu/">Scratch</a> &ndash; This is a visual programming language with a very active community, centered around making games.   There&rsquo;s a lot of resources to help make the class.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/cs">Khan Academy CS</a> &ndash; There is a great new environment in Khan Academy that helps kids learn javascript.  My sense is this would be good for some of the advanced kids.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.codecademy.com/">CodeAcademy</a> &ndash; Similar to Khan Academy, this site helps people learn javascript (and other languages) in a step by step environment.</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve also been intrigued by using MineCraft directly in the class.  You can do a lot of interesting programming and logic exercises simply by using Redstone and Command Blocks.  That said, there&rsquo;s no real guard rails here and I&rsquo;m pretty sure as soon as I let the kids go play MineCraft, they&rsquo;d go off and do whatever they wanted.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s an open source / javascript version of MineCraft called <a href="http://voxeljs.com/">Voxel.js</a>.  I&rsquo;ve tried this with my son, and though it was cool, I am not sure it&rsquo;ll work for a class.  It looks very similar to Minecraft but doesn&rsquo;t have all the features.  I am a bit worried that they will be disappointed by this.  I like it because it will get them to learn a greater part of the coding toolchain (node.js, text editors, html5, javascript, etc) whereas tools like Scratch hide all of that.  I might introduce it later in the cycle if the kids find Scratch too limiting.  Similarly, there are a lot of open source javascript frameworks for gaming.  I haven&rsquo;t looked too closely into these so I&rsquo;m not sure that they&rsquo;ll work.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also looking into &ldquo;physical&rdquo; devices such as Arduino, Lego Mindstorm, or Raspberry Pi to introduce hardware concepts and give them something real to play with.   This might be too ambitious for this class (which is only one day a week for 1.5 hours after school) so perhaps I will do that in another class.</p>

<p>If you know of any other resources (around curriculum, tools, or generally understanding the mindset of a 4th grader), please share in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your idea is a virus - but not in a good way]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/Ideas-are-a-virus-but-not-in-a-good-way/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/Ideas-are-a-virus-but-not-in-a-good-way</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I&rsquo;ve gone from one startup to another, I&rsquo;ve tended to think of ideas as &ldquo;viral&rdquo;.</p>

<p>What I thought that meant was that they spread from one person to the next.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve come to understand that ideas are more than just a meme that spreads from person to person, destined to provide fame and riches.</p>

<p>Ideas can be destructive, and foolish, and completely irrational.</p>

<p>Like the flu, once an idea takes hold, it can be hard to get rid of.</p>

<p>You get a fever, you can&rsquo;t see clearly, and you often don&rsquo;t make sense to others.  You might even be hallucinating.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s really a kind of sickness.  Many founders will often describe themselves as kind of insane, or ill, or something.</p>

<p>They will hallucinate that they are changing the world.</p>

<p>So, be careful about letting your startup idea consume you completely.  You&rsquo;ll get sick and distracted and the fever may not break for months or years.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A simple way to save time at work]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/A-simple-way-to-save-time-at-work/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/A-simple-way-to-save-time-at-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s a good idea to create a list of questions and answers that people commonly ask you at work.</p>

<p>This will save you time and some grief from constant interruption.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create a page or document somewhere (any tool will do), and call it &ldquo;My FAQ&rdquo;.  (Obviously replace &ldquo;My&rdquo; with our name)</li>
<li>Add it to your email signature as a link, and whatever other social tools people can discover you by (your GChat handle, etc)</li>
<li>When new questions come in from people (from any channel), make sure to write them down in your FAQ first.  Then, instead of answering them directly, send a link to the appropriate FAQ article.</li>
<li>Put a link on your FAQ to prompt people to say &ldquo;Thanks&rdquo;.  This will encourage you to keep up your FAQ.</li>
</ul>


<p>Once you&rsquo;ve started to do this, you&rsquo;ll get in the habit and find that the time you save makes up for time spent adding to your FAQ.</p>

<p>What tricks do you use to save time at work?</p>

<p>PS- If you would like a tool that can help you build your own personal FAQs at work, you can try <a href="https://corpqna.com">CorpQNA</a>.  It will create and maintain your FAQ for you, let you share it, and do a lot of Q&amp;A stuff that you might expect if your team really gets into it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coding vs Writing]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/coding-vs-writing/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/coding-vs-writing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As someone who sits in front of a computer all day, I should be writing more on my blog.</p>

<p>When I am coding, I am in a comfortable environment (Visual Studio) and workstation is completely setup for writing</p>

<p>I have always struggled with a good environment for writing.  Currently, I switch between vim and Sublime Text, but I don&#8217;t really find either of those to be effective, since they are lacking tools to help me lookup things and integrate them into my workflow.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s pretty clear that if I am going to write more, it needs to be as easy as coding.</p>

<p>What do you do to make writing easier?</p>

<p>Update! I just discovered <a href ="http://prose.io">Prose.io</a> which is a nice little content editor for github pages.  Perfect!</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chromecast Screensaver]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/chromecast-screensaver/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/chromecast-screensaver</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently got a Google Chromecast, and was looking for a way to push custom images as a screensaver for it.</p>

<p>Though there&#8217;s no obvious &#8220;set it and forget it&#8221; that runs headless, you can easily run the built-in
<a href="https://clients3.google.com/cast/chromecast/home">Chromecast wallpapers</a> in FullScreen mode.</p>

<p>Just click to that page, use the Chromecast extension, and type F11 to put it in full screen mode. </p>

<p><a href="http://www.techhive.com/article/2045755/7-browser-tricks-to-get-the-most-out-of-your-chromecast.html">Hat Tip - TechHive.com</a></p>

<p>If you discover any Chromecast Screensaver apps, please add them in the comments!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rails vs CSharp]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/rails-vs-csharp/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/rails-vs-csharp</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In which I write a few thoughts on Rails v CSharp</p>
<p>I originally published this on Seattle Tech Startups mailing list</p>
<ul>
<li>The market in Seattle is distorted with a lot more startup oriented .NET devs than you will see in just about any other city.</li>
<li>When I tell people that I work on .NET startups in SF, and they are Rails devs, they look at me like I&#8217;m crazy and building my app in COBOL.NET.  They still think ASP.NET == WebForms.</li>
<li>BizSpark is offering effectively 3 years of free hosting to startups.  This is changing the market and getting more new companies to try out .NET</li>
<li>The dynamic features of the CLR / .NET still are not as useful as the dynamic features of Rails.</li>
<li>ASP.NET MVC / WebAPI is on par with Rails</li>
<li>Entity Framework Code First is not as good as Active Record.</li>
<li>People&#8217;s faith in Rails security has been shaken this year by a series of apocolyptic security flaws.</li>
<li>.NET security is very good.</li>
<li>The user model in rails is more extensible and well thought out than the off-the-shelf ASP.NET model.</li>
<li>The rubygems ecoysystem is better than the nuget ecosystem, (and probably always will be)</li>
<li>is mitigated by a lot of javascript based services that function the same way as a gem might.</li>
<li>Azure no longer sucks.</li>
<li>If you believe in OSS as a core part of your being, you will always feel second rate in the .NET world, compared to the Ruby world.</li>
</ul>




]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[ASP.NET MVC Best Practices]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/aspnet-mvc-best-practices/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/aspnet-mvc-best-practices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is work-in-progress list of my ASP.NET Best Practices. They each deserve more explanation plus code samples, which I will eventually write and link to.</p>

<div class="row">

<div class="offset1 span4">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Make your <a href="http://t.co/hdxeE4s5KY">http://t.co/hdxeE4s5KY</a> Controllers partial classes + ViewModels and Actions in the same file <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23dotnet&amp;src=hash">#dotnet</a></p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/355373348609470466">July 11, 2013</a></blockquote>
</div>

<div class="span4">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Make your service class partial and keep DTOs and service methods as method-per-file <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23dotnet&amp;src=hash">#dotnet</a></p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/355373477232001025">July 11, 2013</a></blockquote>
</div>
</div>

<div class="row">
<div class="offset1 span4">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Use ICollection or IList to avoid leaking your Entity Framework IQueryable into your Controller and View <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23dotnet&amp;src=hash">#dotnet</a></p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/355376435436847104">July 11, 2013</a></blockquote>
</div>

<div class="span4">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Create a service per resource (db, search, email, etc) and a master service that your controller calls <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23dotnet&amp;src=hash">#dotnet</a></p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/355377591961661441">July 11, 2013</a></blockquote>
</div>
</div>

<div class="row">
<div class="offset1 span4">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Avoid the code-&gt;run-&gt;debug loop by creating an integration suite to write your db / search / querying code <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23dotnet&amp;src=hash">#dotnet</a></p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/355378129721753600">July 11, 2013</a></blockquote>
</div>
<div class="span4">
	<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Use ViewModels to keep logic out of your views and make them more testable <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23dotnet&amp;src=hash">#dotnet</a></p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/355390310236430337">July 11, 2013</a></blockquote>
</div>

</div>

<script async src="http://douglastarr.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>




]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An intercom.io playbook]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/my-intercom-playbook/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/my-intercom-playbook</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[	<p>At <a href="https://corpqna.com">CorpQNA</a>, we use <a href="http://intercom.io">intercom.io</a> to manage our web CRM.  It&#8217;s a fairly sophisticated product, and there are a few tricks that I&#8217;ve learned that I thought that I would share.</p>

	<h3>Send out your newsletters using tags</h3>
		<p>Avoid using the &#8220;manual&#8221; message to send newsletters.	Using tags lets you easily control large sends, and then also lets you repurpose your content for future users.</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Create a new tag, and tag yourself with it, that says &#8220;Blue Newsletter&#8221;.</li>
			<li>Write your email, and target it at people only with the &#8220;Blue Newsletter&#8221; tag.</li>
			<li>Tag some small % of your users with the &#8220;Blue Newsletter&#8221; and watch open / click rates.</li>
			<li>Monitor open / click rates via intercom.</li>
			<li>Once you are happy with your results - resend it to the whole group.</li>
		</ul>	


	<h3>Use LastContacted to reduce email overload</h3>
		<p>It can be overwhelming to put together a DRIP campaign for your website.  Given intercom&#8217;s interface, it&#8217;s kind of hard to know who is going to receive what message, at what time.</p>

		<p>What this often leads to is users being blasted by multiple emails in too short of a time period.</p>

		<p>Intercom has a field called LastContacted.  In all of your Auto messages, just make sure LastContact > 3 days, so that you don&#8217;t contact your users more than every 3 days, regardless of whatever other rules you&#8217;ve setup.</p>

	<h3>Use a big call to action near the top of your newsletter</h3>

		<p>We&#8217;ve found that most users click the first big link they see.  Maybe this is because they don&#8217;t read the whole newsletter, maybe because they are trained that way, who knows.  In any case, it&#8217;s good to take advantage of that by putting a big call to action in a large font right near the top of your newsletter.  It will probably get the most clicks.</p>

	<h3>Tag your links with Google Analytics Campaigns</h3>
		<p>Assuming you use Google Analytics, you can tag each link separately with the utm_* keywords.  This lets you see how each link is doing.</p>

	<h3>Use Intercom as a lightweight email list for your leads</h3>
		<p>If you have users who are not using your product, but perhaps have signed up for your newsletter, make sure they are on your list by dropping your intercom javascript on the &#8220;Thank you&#8221; page.  Mark these users separate from logged in users.  Beware, though.   With the new intercom pricing, this can be prohibitive since you may have a lot more people signing up for your mailing list than actually using your product, and you are charged by the active user.</p>

	<h3>Copy the intercom playbook</h3>
		<p>If you don&#8217;t know what to do with your email campaign, start by copying the experts.  Here&#8217;s a <a href="http://insideintercom.io/does-your-app-have-a-message-schedule/">great article from intercom</a> on some ideas to include in your campaign.</p>]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
