<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: qna, | Douglas Tarr]]></title>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/categories/qna/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-12T09:08:49-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://douglastarr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Douglas Tarr]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing New Relic on Elastic Beanstalk for Windows and IIS]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/installing-new-relic-on-elastic-beanstalk-for-windows-and-iis/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-24T10:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/installing-new-relic-on-elastic-beanstalk-for-windows-and-iis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently had the experience of getting New Relic to install on an AWS Elastic Beanstalk environment using IIS and Windows.</p>

<p>There are some great tools that make this dead simple on Azure, but on Elastic Beanstalk, it&rsquo;s not quite as simple.   You can&rsquo;t just install using an MSI manually, since Elastic Beanstalk will auto-scale instances.</p>

<p>This means that you need to build it as part of the Elastic Beanstalk configuration.</p>

<ul>
<li>Create a directory called <code>.ebextensions</code> under the root of your project</li>
<li>Create a file called <code>newrelic.config</code> in that directory.  This will be in YAML format (2 spaces per indent)</li>
<li>Make sure to add this file to your .csproj project and include it as content so it copies up with AWS.</li>
<li>Download the latest <a href="https://docs.newrelic.com/docs/dotnet/new-relic-net-installation">.NET MSI from New Relic</a></li>
<li>Upload this MSI to S3 and make it public (everyone should be able to download it)</li>
<li>Get your New Relic license key from your New Relic account</li>
<li>In newrelic.config, copy this in:</li>
</ul>


<p>```
files:
  &ldquo;c:\newrelic\newrelic.msi&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code>source: [Your S3 URL]
</code></pre>

<p>commands:
  install_newrelic:</p>

<pre><code>command: msiexec.exe /i c:\\newrelic\\newrelic.msi NR_LICENSE_KEY=[Your License Key] INSTALLLEVEL=1
</code></pre>

<p>```
*  This should copy down the MSI from your s3 bucket and install new relic with our license key to your instance
*  New Relic should start reporting your instances (called AMAZON-something)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
