<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mvcoders | Douglas Tarr]]></title>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/categories/mvcoders/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-01T10:45:23-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://douglastarr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Douglas Tarr]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coding Class Week 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/coding-class-week-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-01T09:21:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/coding-class-week-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This was the first week of my <a href="/categories/mvcoders">8 Week Coding Class for 4th Graders</a></p>

<p>I ran 2 classes after school (about 5 kids per class) after school.  I was a bit nervous to get started as I had no idea what was going to happen, or if the kids were going to get bored.  We followed the plan that I laid out in my <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-1.md">the fourth grade coding curriculum</a> on Github, with a few modifications.</p>

<h2>After school</h2>

<p>Getting everyone to focus at the beginning was tough.  They came directly from school and were a little bit rambunctious from sitting in class all day.  Some kids immediately booted up their laptops to play a video game and I had to tell them not to.</p>

<h2>Computers</h2>

<p>I asked the kids to bring their own laptops if possible.  I have a series of old laptops and fortunately, most of them worked, even if they were a little bit slow.   I needed Google Chrome installed on each computer, which I had to install on a few of their laptops.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to avoid using any native shell programs since they aren&rsquo;t going to be the same amongst all the laptops that the kids have.  For example, I&rsquo;ve had kids bring Macbooks, Chromebooks and Windows 7 and 8 laptops.  Even trying to get a <a href="http://www.gnu.org/software/bash/">bash shell</a> running on all those environments would have been tough.</p>

<p>In the future, I may look at <a href="http://nitrous.io">Nitrous.io</a> if I do want a terminal that they can all use.  I tried out making a &ldquo;Hello World&rdquo; <a href="http://voxeljs.com">Voxel.js</a> / <a href="http://nodejs.org">Node.js</a> with Nitrous, and that worked.  I may use that in a future class, to show them how you can code your own Minecraft world.</p>

<h2>Introduction</h2>

<p>I asked the kids what they thought programming was.  Some named programming languages like HTML.  One mentioned &ldquo;The Matrix&rdquo; and how they used progrmaming there. A few said Minecraft.  Some said it was a way to get computers to do what you want.  A few had no idea.</p>

<p>I asked them what they wanted to do in the class?  In the first class, they all unanimously said &ldquo;make video games&rdquo;.  Some had very specific ideas about the games that they wanted to make.  In the second class, it was a mix.  One wanted to make a very specific Minecraft plugin that made it easy and safe to make other Minecraft plugins.  One wanted to make it safer to use computers online (he was on a Windows 8 laptop, FWIW).  The rest wanted to make video games.</p>

<p>They responded well (&ldquo;woohoo!&rdquo;) when I told them that this wasn&rsquo;t going to be like a normal class in school where you had to listen to a teacher talk, and that they&rsquo;d spend a lot of time coding.  That said, I did have to calm them down periodically, just like any class.</p>

<h2>ChromeCast</h2>

<p>The class was in our living room, and I used my laptop + <a href="http://www.google.com/intl/en/chrome/devices/chromecast/">ChromeCast</a> to show them videos and code samples on the screen.  This worked out really well &ndash; we watched the <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nKIu9yen5nc">Code.org video</a> in one of the classes, and the kids responded really well to seeing Bill Gates and Mark Zuckerberg on the screen, talking about coding.</p>

<h2>CodeCombat</h2>

<p><img src="https://github-camo.global.ssl.fastly.net/5cbc6e9e49ea8cecd35303f9e62bf27cda4edefa/687474703a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f496c76373352382e706e67" alt="Code Combat Screenshot" /></p>

<p>A few weeks ago, on <a href="http://news.ycombinator.com">Hacker News</a>, I heard about a cool site called <a href="http://codecombat.com">CodeCombat</a> which teaches kids some javascript and coding fundamentals.  There are a series of &ldquo;challenges&rdquo; that the kids have to go through, such as having their knight defeat a troll, move around a maze, and say various things in order.   Overall &ndash; the kids LOVED this game and had a lot of fun.  I think they didn&rsquo;t even realize that they were learning coding.  I heard from one parent that their kid had a lot of fun but didn&rsquo;t learn much. I think this was because they thought they were just playing a game.  But in order to play the game, you have to write a lot of javascript, understand logic flow and how to construct and debug a sophisticated program.  So, I considered it a success because it was a lot of fun.</p>

<p>That said, running the class reminded me of the game <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diner_Dash">Diner Dash</a> for a while. In that game, you are a waitress, and your job is to take and serve complex orders in a diner very quickly.  If you mess up the orders or take too long, customers get mad.  If you do everything right, you get points. I found that with 5 or 6 kids, especially as they get going, they are hitting roadblocks about every minute.   Most of these involved some sort of debugging of their javascript code.  They would say &ldquo;It&rsquo;s not working&rdquo; and I&rsquo;d come over and try to help them figure out what&rsquo;s wrong.   If I spent too much time helping one student, the bugs would back up and I&rsquo;d have a lot of kids unhappy.  If the kids were blocked for too long, they would get frustrated.</p>

<p>One thing I am not sure about is how someone with no programming experience can help kids.  Most of the problems that I was solving for were debugging issues.  These are easy for developers to solve (sometimes) but sometimes they are not!  Some of these problems could be resolved with a more sophisticated user interface.  But making debugging &ldquo;easy&rdquo; is a famously hard problem in computer science.  One example of this problem is the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Halting_problem">halting problem</a>  Ie, trying to detect if a computer is stuck in an infinite loop.   I think this gets easier with visual programming languages since it&rsquo;s easier to stay &ldquo;on the rails&rdquo;.  But, much of the power of coding is still in language based coding, so I want to balance out these two techniques.</p>

<p>That said, whenever the kids solved a problem on their own (ie, fixed a missing parentheses, semicolon, or capitalization), they would get very excited that they accomplished something.  CodeCombat also did a good job of helping them celebrate their victories by showing them a little animation of their knight crushing the enemy or winning.</p>

<h2>Browser Based Coding</h2>

<p>CodeCombat uses two windows &ndash; a game and a javascript editor in a browser.  This does present some challenges.  The coding window loses focus a lot, and the kids expect when they start typing, sometimes nothing would happen.  The game would occasionally get stuck, or the browser would get wonky, and I&rsquo;d have to reset the screen.   At this age (9 + 10 years old), this would be a tough game for the kids to learn without my help.</p>

<p>The kids also needed to learn to type like a software developer would.  Learning how to type as a coder is different than typing words.  I am not teaching them to use advanced coding motions (ie, vim) but there are a set of things that they need to code javascript.  For example, they need to know various characters &ndash; parentheses, semicolon, single and double quotes.  They need to know how to position the cursor on a line and insert a new line below it.  They need to know how to &ldquo;pronounce&rdquo; code.  ie, when I asked them to pronounce &ldquo;this.moveNext();&rdquo;, they said &ldquo;this period move next parentheses parentheses semicolon&rdquo;.   Teaching them how &ldquo;talk in code&rdquo; was a surprising thing that was important to teach.</p>

<h2>CodeClub Software</h2>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-YV1ZHLB3uao/UnGDazlwlCI/AAAAAAAAYlE/K5tPI5iS5JM/w1623-h1217-no/20131030_150608.jpg" alt="CodeClub Software on ChromeCast" /></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve built a little ASP.NET MVC website that gives them logins, lets them take notes, and then guides them through the class using the curriculum that I put on Github.   This mostly worked, but there was a bug in the first class where some of their notes didn&rsquo;t save.   This software is really valuable for parents to see what&rsquo;s going on, and it gives me a way to communicate and guide the class.</p>

<h2>Second Class</h2>

<p>The goal of the next class is to introduce them to <a href="http://scratch.mit.edu">MIT Scratch</a> which is a visual environment for learning to make games and animations.  I&rsquo;m working on the curriculum now, so check back in a week or so to see how that went.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Open Source Coding Curriculum]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/an-open-source-coding-curriculum/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-27T11:48:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/an-open-source-coding-curriculum</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://github.global.ssl.fastly.net/images/modules/training/professortocat.png" alt="Github Teacher Logo" /></p>

<p>One of the biggest challenges in teaching a coding class is the curriculum.  What are the kids going to do during each class?  How do we keep them challenged?  Is the class something that they enjoy, or not?</p>

<h2>Discovering Curriculums Online</h2>

<p>I have been feverishly searching the internet for a coding curriculum that works for an in-person coding class.  There are a lot of resources that are geared toward online classes, but very few for in person classes.</p>

<p>There are a lot of people thinking about this same problem right now.  Every day, I hear about parents and teachers trying to teach their kids to code, and going online to figure out how to do it.</p>

<h2>Coding Curriculum on GitHub</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m putting the <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons">curriculum I&rsquo;m building</a> on Github so that other parents and teachers can learn from it, or use it for their own needs.  <a href="https://github.com">Github</a> is a tool that is used by software developers to share and discover code.  But, it&rsquo;s also great for sharing and discovering any &ldquo;structured&rdquo; data.  Since I&rsquo;m using github, you can change the curriculum as you need for your own purposes (just sign up for a Github account and then click the &ldquo;Fork&rdquo; button on the project)</p>

<p>My curriculum is fairly straightforward &ndash; it&rsquo;s a way to guide me through an 90 minutes with 4 or 5 kids.  I&rsquo;ve decided to use GitHub to host the curriculum, and I&rsquo;m using a simple language called MarkDown to write the curriculum.  MarkDown is like HTML, but a bit easier to write.  For instance, you can just write text, with no formatting, and it&rsquo;s smart enough to make things format fairly nicely.  It also supports most of the basic web formats you&rsquo;d expect &ndash; images, links, etc.  It&rsquo;s a bit more technical than writing an email (since there are a few special codes) but if you are teaching a coding class, you probably won&rsquo;t mind a few more codes, right?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m writing the curriculum as I go, since I need to see how students respond to each class to structure the next one.  My best guess on how the class will go is available on Github.  You can &ldquo;star&rdquo; the repository on Github if you want to follow along as i change it.  You can also use the <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/issues">Issues feature</a> of Github to provide comments on the curriculum itself.  Finally, if you want to make your own curriculum, you can <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/fork">Fork it</a> and make your own.  There will be a lot of changes (until the end of December 2013) so beware if you are trying to stay &ldquo;in sync&rdquo; with me.</p>

<p>View the curriculum here:</p>

<h3><a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/tree/master/4th-grade-coders">4th Grade Coding Class on Github</a></h3>

<h2>CodeClub software</h2>

<p>A few months ago, it was Eli&rsquo;s birthday, and we invited his friends over to play MineCraft.  I brought out some of my old laptops, and some of the kids brought their own.  I tried to get everyone setup to play Minecraft on our network, and that took some time, even with just 8 or 10 kids.</p>

<p>What I learned from that experience was that even having some basic links and setup in a web browser can go a long way to making the class more effecient.</p>

<p>The kids I&rsquo;m working with don&rsquo;t all have email addresses &ndash; so I need a way to communicate with them as well, give them links, and give parents a way to follow what their kids are working on.</p>

<p>So, I&rsquo;ve decided to write some software called <a href="http://github.com/tarr11/codeclub">CodeClub</a> that lets you pull in any ccurriculum available on Github and use it to run your own class. The software will be free, open source, and MIT licensed.  Right now, that repository is blank since the code is pretty rough.</p>

<p>CodeClub is what we are going to be using in the class.  Once it&rsquo;s a little better, I&rsquo;ll put it up with some instructions on how you can easily host it yourself.</p>

<p>First class starts tomorrow, we are all very excited to get started.  Stay tuned on my blog to learn how it goes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[3 Types of Programming Classes for Kids]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/3-types-of-programming-classes-for-kids/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-24T09:43:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/3-types-of-programming-classes-for-kids</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been doing a lot of research on how to effectively make a curriculum for the 4th Graders that I am teaching.  Turns out, it&rsquo;s not easy!</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been struggling to figure out what my role is in this experience.  For example, there are many <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massive_open_online_course">MOOCs</a> (<a href="http://khanacademy.org">Khan Academy</a>, <a href="http://codeacademy.com">Code Academy</a> ) out there that essentially provide a self-directed learning environment.  There are some hybrid environments like <a href="http://tynker.com">Tynker</a> that provide a more structured environment which helps teachers run a larger class, but still get into some depth around programming.  It would be a waste of time for me to have them just simply turn on computers and point them at Khan Academy.</p>

<p>My experience watching my children try to use these tools is that they work well for everything &hellip; except programming.  It is really hard to make a perfectly self-contained, understandable, modular programming environment where the kids don&rsquo;t go off the rails.  That said &ndash; they are great to use when someone can help get past roadblocks, bugs in software, and design issues that make the software confusing. I think online or self-directed curricula are very important, but I think that if kids (especially younger kids) are left to their own on these programs, they will get stuck and discouraged, even with the best designed programs.</p>

<p>So, where does that leave us?  Can we adopt an online curriculum for our class or do we have to build our own?<br/>
There are some curricula out there, especially built around tools like <a href="http://scratch.mit.edu">MIT Scratch</a>.
The curriculum you use or develop is highly dependent on the kind of structure you put towards your class.  This stuff is probably pretty obvious to anyone who has been involved professionally in education (teachers, etc) but it&rsquo;s a new discovery for me.</p>

<p>I would categorize the curriculum into 3 groups (classes, teams, and clubs)</p>

<h2>The Class</h2>

<p>The entire class is going to be learning the exact same thing, at the same time.  This seems to be the model taken by schools.  It&rsquo;s also a valuable way to go if you have a large group of kids (more than 8 or 10) since you really won&rsquo;t have the time to give them individual attention.  You are trading some creativity and self-direction for scale.  It&rsquo;s also harder to get kids to be excited by a class.</p>

<h2>The Team</h2>

<p>You are teaching them some skills but there&rsquo;s a lot of free time and everyone need not learn the same thing.  There&rsquo;s a concept of working together as a team and collaborating.  Teams can be smaller, and different kids can specialize in different areas.  There&rsquo;s a sense of grouping by age and at the end of the &ldquo;season&rdquo; you should have learned some valuable skills.  You might have a competition or challenge as well.</p>

<h2>The Club</h2>

<p>You are there to provide some resources and keep everyone moving forward, but it&rsquo;s more self-directed.  My guess is that this model works really well in high school, where the kids have self-selected into wanting to participate and have the ability to solve more in depth problems on their own.  You are offering lots of opportunities and an environment for individual creativity and collaboration.</p>

<p>For the <a href="/categories/mvcoders">MVCoders</a> group, I am going to use the &ldquo;Team&rdquo; approach since I am dealing with a small group of motivated kids.</p>

<h2>Future Questions To Address</h2>

<ul>
<li>Visual Programming Languages (ie, Scratch) vs Text based Languages (javascript)</li>
<li>What is an appropriate amount of &ldquo;help&rdquo; to give students</li>
<li>As a developer, how much custom code should I be writing myself?</li>
<li>What is the relationship of a coding class to other traditional classes?</li>
<li>What expectations does everyone (parents, kids, teachers, etc) have for the class?</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Teaching Coding to 4th Graders]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/Teaching-Coding-to-4th-graders/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/Teaching-Coding-to-4th-graders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve decided to teach coding to some 4th graders after school, including my son and about 7 other kids.</p>

<p>My background is as a software developer, but teaching is new to me.</p>

<p>So, I&rsquo;m planning on writing some blog entries to keep notes on what I&rsquo;ve learned and how I&rsquo;m structuring the class.  You can follow along about it using the <a href="/categories/mvcoders">mvcoders</a> tag in my blog.</p>

<p>My son really enjoys Minecraft, to the point where he religiously watches every &ldquo;How-To&rdquo; video on YouTube about fun ways to use Redstone and Command Blocks to do neat things.</p>

<p>I really want to encourage kids to have fun programming.  It is so much different now and there are a ton of resources to use that don&rsquo;t require kids to get immersed in the guts of the OS to learn some basic coding.</p>

<p>My challenge has been to find a good curriculum to teach, and figure out how to best structure for the class so that all of the kids have a great experience.</p>

<p>Resources I&rsquo;m looking at using:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://scratch.mit.edu/">Scratch</a> &ndash; This is a visual programming language with a very active community, centered around making games.   There&rsquo;s a lot of resources to help make the class.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/cs">Khan Academy CS</a> &ndash; There is a great new environment in Khan Academy that helps kids learn javascript.  My sense is this would be good for some of the advanced kids.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.codecademy.com/">CodeAcademy</a> &ndash; Similar to Khan Academy, this site helps people learn javascript (and other languages) in a step by step environment.</li>
</ul>


<p>I&rsquo;ve also been intrigued by using MineCraft directly in the class.  You can do a lot of interesting programming and logic exercises simply by using Redstone and Command Blocks.  That said, there&rsquo;s no real guard rails here and I&rsquo;m pretty sure as soon as I let the kids go play MineCraft, they&rsquo;d go off and do whatever they wanted.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s an open source / javascript version of MineCraft called <a href="http://voxeljs.com/">Voxel.js</a>.  I&rsquo;ve tried this with my son, and though it was cool, I am not sure it&rsquo;ll work for a class.  It looks very similar to Minecraft but doesn&rsquo;t have all the features.  I am a bit worried that they will be disappointed by this.  I like it because it will get them to learn a greater part of the coding toolchain (node.js, text editors, html5, javascript, etc) whereas tools like Scratch hide all of that.  I might introduce it later in the cycle if the kids find Scratch too limiting.  Similarly, there are a lot of open source javascript frameworks for gaming.  I haven&rsquo;t looked too closely into these so I&rsquo;m not sure that they&rsquo;ll work.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also looking into &ldquo;physical&rdquo; devices such as Arduino, Lego Mindstorm, or Raspberry Pi to introduce hardware concepts and give them something real to play with.   This might be too ambitious for this class (which is only one day a week for 1.5 hours after school) so perhaps I will do that in another class.</p>

<p>If you know of any other resources (around curriculum, tools, or generally understanding the mindset of a 4th grader), please share in the comments!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
