<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mvcoders | Douglas Tarr]]></title>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/categories/mvcoders/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://douglastarr.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-14T09:57:34-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://douglastarr.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Douglas Tarr]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Working on our Scratch game - Week 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/working-on-our-scratch-game-week-7/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-14T09:50:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/working-on-our-scratch-game-week-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The promise of this class is that kids would have their own working game.  So, this week, they just got to work on their game using all that they knew about Scratch.</p>

<p>Everyone worked on their individual games, and I saw some really cool ideas.</p>

<p>Rather than talk to much about the class, I&rsquo;ve started to reflect on what I&rsquo;ve learned about teaching coding.</p>

<h2>Learnings</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Laptops are hard for kids to code on.  We hit lots of frustrating bugs related to slow latops, using touchpads, and weird browser interactions.</p></li>
<li><p>The kids love Scratch!   It lets them express their creativity in a new way.</p></li>
<li><p>Most of the problems in class happen when their code &ldquo;doesn&rsquo;t work&rdquo;.  Then, they are completely blocked.  Sometimes, it&rsquo;s not obvious (even to me) what happened and why it doesn&rsquo;t work, and can take me a while to figure it out.    As they try to build more sophisticated programs, the problems get harder to solve.</p></li>
<li><p> Kids enjoy coding together &ndash; they are always looking at what each other is working on and makes it more fun.</p></li>
<li><p>Scheduling is painful.  Every child has so much to do in their schedule, and they want to be in class with a particular set of other kids, and it quickly turns into a very hard math problem.   I&rsquo;ve got a set of other kids who might want to participate, but I am having trouble integrating the schedules effectively.</p></li>
<li><p>Coding is more than just computer science math.  Kids are spending a lot of their time making songs, drawing, creating little &ldquo;theatrical animations&rdquo;.</p></li>
<li><p>There&rsquo;s a lot of math that they haven&rsquo;t yet learned in school.  They have to master Cartesian coordinates, how to manipulate negative numbers, and a lot of other things.  So, I find myself teaching a lot of math so that you can get your game to have a character jump up and down.</p></li>
<li><p>We probably don&rsquo;t need to &ldquo;move on&rdquo; from Scratch for a while.  There is a lot to do there and I think it will take some time to master.</p></li>
<li><p>Different kids like different things.  I&rsquo;ve got a few kids who love performing, music and singing, and they spend a lot of their time making &ldquo;arrangements&rdquo;.  Some others just love hacking on video games.  Some are just naturally curious and enjoy learning technologies.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Next Steps</h2>

<p>Next week is our final week of this 8 week class, and hopefully the kids will feel like it was enjoyable and that they learned some new things about computers and programming.</p>

<p>We are going to start a new session in the new year, and I&rsquo;m pleased to announce that 100% of the kids are going to continue to participate.   Based on what I&rsquo;ve learned, I&rsquo;m working on some changes that I think will make the experience better.  Stay tuned, I&rsquo;ll announce those next week.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clones and variables - Coding Class Week 6]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/clones-and-variables-coding-class-week-6/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-06T08:58:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/clones-and-variables-coding-class-week-6</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week was a bit of a stretch.  I wanted to teach the kids about clones.  This is a concept that&rsquo;s used fairly extensively in video games.</p>

<h2>Video</h2>

<p>We watched this video &ndash; someone basically modeled minecraft in a 3D toolkit.  I wanted them to see clones and physics in action.</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/o702In0aI5E" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>Clones</h2>

<p><img src="/images/clones.jpg" alt="Clones" /></p>

<p>Clones are copies of things.  The kids have been learning to make a game, but the games tend to have very few characters, and they have to script them out individually.  This can be tedious and still feel fairly manual.</p>

<p>Part of the magic of coding is when you start building lots of objects that interact with each other.   Much of this involves math and physics, so that you can simulate bouncing, gravity, and other real world phenomena.</p>

<p>However, I figured that the kids would be far enough along that they could try.</p>

<h2>Shoot the Penguin</h2>

<p><img src="/images/shoot-the-penguin.png" alt="Shoot the penguin" /></p>

<p>We were going to make a simple game  &ndash; I just called it &ldquo;Shoot the Penguin&rdquo;.  Make a gun, make a bullet, make a penguin.   If the bullet touches the penguin, the penguin dies.</p>

<p>I gave them an example of a gun that shoots a bullet.  Some of the kids had previously figured out how to do this; They had a gun sprite and a bullet sprite and when they hit the space bar, the bullet sprite started moving until it hit the edge.</p>

<h2>Direction, Position, and Variables</h2>

<p>At some point, most of the kids had figured out how to make the gun shoot a bullet, and even kill the penguin.</p>

<p>Then, the next goal was to aim the gun.   This was useful because the kids naturally start complaining that their gun doesn&rsquo;t work too well, since it won&rsquo;t aim, and the bullet sometimes doesn&rsquo;t shoot out of the gun.  So, we had to create some global variables to store the position of the gun, and then copy those to the bullet so that the bullet knew which direction to go.</p>

<h2>Scratch Limitations, and Bugs</h2>

<p>Scratch is very &ldquo;opionated&rdquo;, and only comes with a subset of features available in modern programming languages.  It&rsquo;d be better if it was more object oriented, such that I could query the gun&rsquo;s position, instead of copying into a global variable.  This would have been more natural for the kids to understand.  Copying around variables around is a little bit confusing and messy.</p>

<p>We also ran into some bugs &ndash; sprites would just simply not rotate correctly sometimes, and we had to delete them and re-add them.  It was also common for kids to build a complicated sprite, but put it in the wrong place (ie, as a backdrop or as a costume attached to a different sprite)  When they finally realized they did it wrong, they had no idea how to move it.</p>

<p>We finally figured out that you do it by downloading the sprite to your local computer, then uploading again.  Copy/paste would have been better.</p>

<p>Also, renaming variables and sprites tends to break script blocks, which don&rsquo;t update their references always.  So, either name your variables and sprites up front, or don&rsquo;t bother.</p>

<h2>Next Week</h2>

<p>I keep meaning to let the kids just build in class, and not really teach them anything.  I think for the last 2 weeks, that&rsquo;s what we&rsquo;ll do.  They can be creative, and I&rsquo;ll just help them as they finish their &ldquo;final projects&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scratch Variables and Lists - Coding Class Week 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/scratch-variables-and-lists-coding-class-week-5/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-27T13:44:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/scratch-variables-and-lists-coding-class-week-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week we learned about variables and lists.</p>

<h2>How Computers Work</h2>

<p>We watched this Ted video on how computers work.  I&rsquo;m not sure any of it sunk in, but it was a good way to visualize how a computer processes things.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/AkFi90lZmXA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>Keeping Score</h2>

<p>Rather than present variables as an abstract concept, I asked the kids if they wanted to keep score in their games.  Most of them did, a few weren&rsquo;t sure.</p>

<p>So, we made a game this week where we made a map, animated a sprite, and collected coins, which would increase their score.</p>

<p>Once their score got a certain point, they would win.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example from one of the students
<img src="/images/coin-game.png" alt="Coin Game" /></p>

<h2>Math, Physics, Art, and Communication</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve noticed that the kids have to quickly learn a lot of advanced concepts in order to make their game work.  For example, they have to understand negative numbers, multiplication, and graphs.</p>

<p>They inevitably start to make fairly complex designs, and they have to learn how to keep things organized and modular.</p>

<p>Several kids have wanted to make their character &ldquo;jump&rdquo;, which involves simulating physics (gravity, velocity, etc)</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s pretty amazing what they will learn quickly enough if they are motivated.</p>

<p>My sense is that programming games is a great way to teach just about any subject at this age.  They have to quickly master a concept and if they don&rsquo;t, their program won&rsquo;t work.</p>

<h2>Finishing our game</h2>

<p>At this point, the kids may not know it, but they&rsquo;ve got a completely working game!  We will spend the remaining few weeks fine tuning our games and adding more features.</p>

<h2>Code Club HQ</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve rented a space for Code Club Headquarters, at 38 Miller Ave in Mill Valley.  I&rsquo;m very excited to put some cool stuff in there and run a few more classes.</p>

<p>Follow along here on this blog and <a href="http://facebook.com/mvcodeclub">become a fan on Facebook</a></p>

<p>If you live in Marin and are interested in having your child participate, please <a href="http://www.mvcodeclub.com/home/winterschedule">check out the schedule</a> on the <a href="http://www.mvcodeclub.com">mvcodeclub.com website</a></p>

<h2>Github</h2>

<p>As always, this class is available on <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-5.md">Github</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Messages and Animation - Coding Class Week 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/messages-and-animation-coding-class-week-4/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-21T08:30:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/messages-and-animation-coding-class-week-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The past 3 weeks, the kids have been learning a lot of things.  How to interact with Scratch, basic programming concepts, and some basic computer skills.</p>

<p>This week, we spent a little time learning something new (events and message passing) but most of the time, I wanted the kids to be focused on building something.</p>

<h2>Unity Video</h2>

<p>We watched this short time lapse video of someone building a game scene in Unity 3D. This looks more like the games that they play on consoles at home.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/Z2ZX9soqOz4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<h2>Message Passing</h2>

<p>Our goal this week was for the kids to learn about how to animate a story.  The tools in Scratch for doing this are pretty light &ndash; they don&rsquo;t really support a timeline UI for keyframing, so there&rsquo;s a lot of manual counting going on in order to synchronize your characters.</p>

<p>I wanted to teach them about message passing, which is a powerful concept that lets them control their animations via events, as opposed to trying to coordinate timing.</p>

<h2>Animation Challenge</h2>

<p>I presented the kids with a challenge &ndash; they had to animate a story, but they were only allowed to press one button to start it, and then it needed to run on its own (sort of like tipping over dominoes)
<img src="/images/dominoes.jpg" alt="Dominoes" /></p>

<p>They had gotten comfortable with event based processing, where they were controlling the animation sort of like a puppet show.  ie., press &ldquo;j&rdquo; and a character will jump.  I wanted them to use messages to instead say &ldquo;when this sprite is finished, it broadcasts a message&rdquo;.  And then, another sprite would listen for that</p>

<p>They spent much of the class working in teams of two, coming up with a story and then trying to animate it.  I liked this model because they would learn based on what they needed, as opposed to just going through and learning every command in the platform.</p>

<p>They loved to record sounds and have their characters do things together.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example of one of the animations (based on Pokemon) the kids put together:</p>

<iframe allowtransparency="true" width="485" height="402" src="http://scratch.mit.edu/projects/embed/14440381/?autostart=false" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Pretty impressive for some 4th graders who did this in about an hour!</p>

<h2>Computers, Creativity, Collaboration and Communication</h2>

<p>I spent some time thinking about the the role of a computer in the creative process.  There is a danger that because computers are powerful devices, they can have a hypnotic effect on the kids.</p>

<p>I wanted the kids to think about what they wanted to build, instead of just clicking around the computer.  This is an important skill for them to learn &ndash; these are just tools and they need to use the tools, not have the tools use them.</p>

<p>So, they spent a few minutes discussing what they wanted to build.  This was somewhat challenging and overwhelming.  A lot of them just wanted to mess around and build it that way.  I think that&rsquo;s fine, but I also wanted them to have their own point of view.</p>

<p>Some of the kids have more experience than others, and I wanted them to learn how to work together and teach each other.  If they are just working alone, they might as well be at home!  So, I spend some time each class trying to get them to work together, communicate, and solve problems together.  Since I&rsquo;ve put them on time limits for this project, that can be somewhat stressful.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a good skill for them to learn how to manage their time and their communication under time pressure.</p>

<h2>Advanced Class + Another Intro Class In January</h2>

<p>We are going to have an advanced class starting in January.  I think it still will be focused around Scratch &ndash; there is a lot to learn here and I&rsquo;d like them to get a bit more mastery before we move on to more complex topics.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m also thinking about running another Intro class &ndash; this is for 4th graders, but it could also work for 3rd and 5th graders as well.  I&rsquo;m hoping to include more girls as well, to balance things out.</p>

<p>If you are interested, please <a href="/contact.html">contact me</a></p>

<h2>Mill Valley Code Club Website, Facebook, and HQ</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve finally got a the <a href="http://www.mvcodeclub.com">Mill Valley Code Club Website</a> setup.  This is where the kids log in, keep notes, and learn about new lessons.  I&rsquo;ll probably improve it more over time.</p>

<p>Also, I&rsquo;ve setup a <a href="http://www.facebook.com/mvcodeclub">Facebook Page</a> and a <a href="http://twitter.com/mvcodeclub">Twitter</a> if you are interested in following along.</p>

<h2>Code Club HQ?</h2>

<p>I am looking at renting out a small space in downtown Mill Valley, to run Code Club classes.  We&rsquo;ve been running out of my house which has been fine, but things get a little hectic, and there&rsquo;s a lot of setup and teardown that I have to do in our living room.</p>

<p>If we have a space, I can add some better hardware.  I have my eye on a <a href="http://www.makerbot.com">Makerbot</a> for example, which would be a fun thing for the kids to play with.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll probably also get a server that we can run Minecraft on, and a bunch of other fun stuff like <a href="http://arduino.cc">Arduino</a>, <a href="http://www.raspberrypi.org">Raspberry Pi</a> etc.</p>

<h2>Github</h2>

<p>As always, <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-4.md">this weeks lesson plan</a> is on Github.  Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Drawing and Painting - Coding Class Week 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://douglastarr.com/drawing-and-painting-coding-class-week-3/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-15T08:52:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://douglastarr.com/drawing-and-painting-coding-class-week-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Originally, my plan for this week was to run a series of Scratch Challenges (make an animated story, a maze, etc).</p>

<p> I had Eli try one out, and I quickly realized that a lot of time is spent on creating sprites.  So, I decided to completely focus the class on drawing and painting.</p>

<p>To start the class, we watched this timelapse video of someone making a game character in Illustrator.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://douglastarr.com//www.youtube.com/embed/k2xYSCNysS0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>This gave the kids an idea of what is possible.  Timelapse videos have a &ldquo;magic&rdquo; to them and I noticed that the kids were mesmerized by it.  They were certainly still chatting and joking (&ldquo;hey that kind of looks like the guy who works at Jamba Juice!&rdquo;) but they were paying attention.</p>

<h2>Drawing and Painting Happy Faces in Scratch</h2>

<p>It turns out that Scratch comes with a fairly decent draw/paint tool.  It&rsquo;s like a simplified version of Adobe Illustrator / Photoshop.</p>

<p>When presented with a drawing or painting tool online, kids immediately just go for a paintbrush and predictably have a hard time making something look good.</p>

<p>Pictures of faces tend to look like very messy.  I had the kids go through and try to make &ldquo;better&rdquo; happy faces so that they could understand why it&rsquo;s better to use vector based methods for drawing instead of bitmap methods.</p>

<p>My goal for the class was to get them to understand what the tools (especially the vector tools) do so that they could make and remix existing vector illustrations.</p>

<p>We learned about painting (bitmaps) and drawing (vectors) and what you could do with each.</p>

<p><img src="/images/animation.gif" alt="Happy Face Progression" /></p>

<p>We learned how to make shapes, fill them in, resize and reshape them.  We also learned how to group and ungroup shapes in vector mode, and the difference between resizing shapes in bitmap vs vector.</p>

<h2>Remixing</h2>

<p>The &ldquo;a-ha&rdquo; moment of the class was then they realized that they could go to the Scratch sprite library, grab a vector based sprite, and then &ldquo;re-mix&rdquo; it to their needs.
<img src="/images/gobo-anim.gif" alt="Gobo" /></p>

<p>We had about 5 or 10 minutes at the end &ndash; I asked the kids to try and make a few drawings and see if they could animate them (using what they learned from last week)  A few of them (who were more comfortable) were able to do this.  Most had a hard time recalling how to connect these two things.</p>

<h2>Speed, Focus and Fun</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;re still having some challenges around getting everyone to focus.  I find myself having to use &ldquo;teacher-voice&rdquo; more than I&rsquo;d like.  I could see some yawns at the beginning of class after a hard day at school.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also noticed that sometimes, the kids just are in there, doing their own thing, and not totally paying attention to what I&rsquo;m having them learn.  That&rsquo;s ok (that&rsquo;s exactly how I was as a kid their age), but I try to go around and make sure everyone gets the gist of the lesson.</p>

<p>And then there was this&hellip;</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>OH in <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23mvcodeclub&amp;src=hash">#mvcodeclub</a> yesterday - &quot;OOOOH, If I make the boogers into sprites, I can make them drip down the squirrel&#39;s nose!&quot;</p>&mdash; Douglas Tarr (@tarr11) <a href="https://twitter.com/tarr11/statuses/400341894791589888">November 12, 2013</a></blockquote>


<script async src="http://douglastarr.com//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>We are literally blazing through Scratch in a really short time.  These kids are learning a lot quickly, but that does lead to some frustration when they don&rsquo;t pick something up as quickly as they&rsquo;d like.</p>

<p>I can sometimes see some frustration when it takes a little longer than they had hoped to figure something out.  It&rsquo;s ok if they don&rsquo;t &ldquo;perfect&rdquo; a skill before moving on to the next one.  I can sense that some of them want to spend more time before moving on.</p>

<p>That said, it seems like everyone is having a great time.</p>

<h2>Next Week</h2>

<p>Next week we are going to work together on teams.  We&rsquo;ll use some of the lessons that we learned to do some challenges together.</p>

<h2>Github</h2>

<p>As always, this lesson is available on Github here &ndash; <a href="https://github.com/tarr11/coding-lessons/blob/master/4th-grade-coders/lesson-3.md">Lesson 3 on Github</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
